[Music]
Heat. Heat. N.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello and welcome to episode 267 of the
Askavget show. I hope everybody is doing
great. Uh this is a geopolitics episode.
So I will take questions only about
geopolitics. I hope that should be uh
that is understood by everybody. So with
that said um and and today is going to
be a 2-hour episode. I will not extend
it to 3 hours. Sometimes uh it gets too
long. So we'll keep it two two hours
which has usually been the the standard
uh length of these shows. So let's see
who all is there on the live chat. I can
see Yan Kumar Bhujel from Bhutan. I can
see Lakshmi Ka ready always ready.
Goresh Balgi exgodfather X Alvin
Rodriguez Mr. Jam Radhira, Agni Varna,
Moonlight Sonata 123, Sunkit 9064,
Shashank Koshik 6681,
uh, Pranav 581, Latangi Suresh, Hitanchu
Meta 26, 2066 from Gujarat, Ganesha 19,
Jaganath, Shashank Koshik once again,
uh, Tripi Mishra, Namaste, Heisenberg
from Rajasthan, Ulas 8156, Aman Jot
Singh, bin Salman, Kumar Kanesh,
Kaneshk 19, Jimmy Lee, Queen Babar,
Geopolitical Dub from Indor, Shri Ram
Chandra,
Jes
Lee. Who else do we have? Sankit Amar
Singh, Jotir
Mai, Ashtoh Dkar, Kumar Kanesh again,
Yati. Who else do we have? Maklavin 69
Ram Ram Anil Gupta Hershit Roule Sel
Sharma Dungar Singh Chawan hello Bresh
SK Raju
Chigi Cherala
TPP4739
Chavda Supremacy Aush Agni Vana
Usharo
Mateo
uh Anthony Yadav Rajat Duhan Chandan
Pande Manish Shakaro Rakav Shind Jay
Kumaran Kanishes 19
Shesh Mitra Sul Sharma who else do we
have uh U MK and so many other people
all right
so um let Jri Jesus somebody is saying
Priyanka is there uh and so on so okay
let's take some questions let's take
some questions today I will take
questions from the super chat the entire
week I have taken question from the live
chat. So let's take some super chat
questions. Uh please ensure that you
only ask geopolitics questions today. I
will not be able to take questions that
are not about geopolitics. I hope that
is very clear from the very beginning.
It's there in the title itself. So
should be and it's also there in the pin
ch pin uh chat. So chat message uh Kumar
Karish says is it a coincidence that
first we had Kalistthani issue in North
America then a regime change in uh East
Pakistan and now India Pakistan war
happened all anti-India activity in a
span of 2 years. Well uh the Kalistthan
issue in North America is a very old
issue. It's been around since the 1980s
essentially. Okay. Uh it was Kalistthani
terrorists, Canadian Kalistthani
terrorists who blew up the the Air India
aircraft uh the Kaneska aircraft, one of
the most heinous uh terrorist attacks in
history. So it's there. It's been there
for a long time and typically the
Kalistthani uh terrorists have been
based in Canada. You had this Hard Singh
Nijar fellow who was an illegal
immigrant into Canada. I don't know how
he acquired Canadian citizen citizenship
despite lying on his visa uh uh
application and whatnot and being
convicted of various crimes but he
became a Canadian citizen. So if you're
a terrorist and if you hate India and if
you're Kalistthani, you're welcome to
get Canadian citizenship apparently. And
then we have that the Gur Patwan Singh
Panun fellow who is a who is an American
Kalistthani terrorist, a US citizen. So
we've had this for a long time. It's not
something that's happened in the past
two years. First of all, let's
understand that. Okay. So look, Canada
is not some active geopolitical player.
Canada is a nice nice country. It's see
the Canadians are the nicest North
Americans you'll meet anywhere in the
world. Super nice people. But the
government of Canada is an extension of
the US empire. In other words, what I
mean to say is that Canada is the US
vasal and they will do whatever the US
uh instructs them to do. That's how
that's what the deal is.
uh so the US has always sought to uh
India's rise India's growth
because India has the potential of
becoming a next the next China so to say
if we get our things right which is a
big deal which is a big if right but if
we get our our things right internally
we can become the next China we have all
the potential and the US is cognizant of
the potential and they will do all it
takes everything it takes to keep us
down and to ensure we don't rise beyond
a certain certain level right we don't
grow beyond a certain level economically
and and so on and that's why the
Kalistan issue exists that's why
Pakistan and east and west Pakistan
exists to keep India hemmed in to keep
India off balance to keep India um
counterbalanced and that's why the
Americans are okay with China you know
working with Pakistan and East Pakistan
and West Pakistan both and China attemp
China China attempting to encircle India
in the subcontinent so so and so on the
US is okay with that as long as China
does something that helps the US uh so
this Khalistan issue is not something
new. Um regime change yes it happened in
all in the past two three years. The
regime change in west Pakistan happened
in 2022. Imran Khan was ousted. He was
very pro-China and a pro- US government
came to power. Uh puppet government.
Then there was regime change in East
Pakistan like I predicted several months
before before it happened. Um and then
you had the India Pakistan war and so
on. So you can see an increase in the uh
in the level of activity against India
in in a very coordinated manner. So you
are definitely right about the pattern
that you're witnessing. But please note
that the Kalistthan issue in in North
America is an old issue. It's been
around since at least the 1980s. Uh Agni
Vana, thank you very much.
Uh Sankit says damnation of leadership
Tibet then again v secular. I don't know
what it means sir.
Um, Kumar Kaneshka says, "Is the crap
education system a geopolitical tool
imposed by the west to keep us mediocre
and stop us from learning how to think
and uh all that and building
technology?" This is so that the west
could be the automatic land of
opportunity and we can you know export
our skills and talent and brains and
intelligent people and best people to
the west. Is it a geopolitical tool
imposed by the west? Well, see the
education system that we have, its roots
go back to the 19th century to the
infamous Lord Macaulay. So he
destroyed essentially the Indian
education system, the indigenous
education system that we still had and
then the British imposed their crap
version of the education system on us
and that's what we still have. It hasn't
changed much. Yeah, we we it's sure we
do give degrees in computer science
these days. We give MBAs. There were no
MBAs in the 19th century. There was no
computer science in the 19th century.
But the way things are taught and the
way the educ education structure system
is structured and the way education is
imparted and all of that it is still
exactly the same as it was in the 19th
century. So the objective of the British
imposed education system was to mentally
colonized colonize Indians. It was to
make English the primary dominant
language in India which would have the
effect of marginalizing our indigenous
languages and it produces people like me
who are more comfortable speaking
English than their own languages. Right?
At least I'm aware of it. At least I
don't have an inferiority complex. But
most Indians are saddled with this
massive crushing inferiority complex
about being brown, about being Indian.
And they imagine that anybody who's
non-Indian is automatically superior to
them. Anybody who speaks English with a
certain extent accent is superior to
them and so on. So this was imposed by
the British with the objective of
mentally colonizing Indians and the
objective was to mass-roduce clerks and
peons
people with good handwriting people who
can take orders not people who can ask
questions. So the entire education
system was structured in a way that you
are not allowed to ask questions. What
is the correct way of learning
something? It is to ask questions.
That's to ask question upon question and
to learn how to ask questions, how to
structure the questions, how to sequence
the questions. That that's how you
learn. That is the correct way of
learning. But you all are taught that
the right way to learn is by memorizing.
It is by and and the teacher is the one
who asks questions and you are the one
who answer. It should be the other way
around. But you don't you don't
understand it because you've never seen
that in real life in your entire
lifetimes, right? You've never seen
that. So you can't imagine a world in
which you can actually learn better by
asking questions instead of answering
questions. So the objective was to
mentally colonize us. The objective was
to mentally lobotomize us. It was to
make sure that our intellect doesn't
rise beyond a certain level. Which is
why you see it all over the place today.
The average intelligence of Indians.
You're not born dumb. You're not born
stupid. But you are made stupid. Your
intellect is smashed out of you by the
education system. The objective is to
you know ensure there are no leaders in
India. There should be no leadership
potential in India by by not teaching
you what leadership is by not teaching
you what the national interest is. So
the objective was to keep India
perpetually colonized.
Now the same education system today is a
fantastic geopolitical tool because
Indians don't understand geopolitics.
Indians don't understand what the
national interest is. If I ask any of
you, my dear viewers who are watching
right now, what's the Indian national
interest? Give me the various this the
main core parameters of the Indian
national interest. I wonder how many of
you can answer that. Your teachers won't
be able to answer it. They'll answer
some nonsense.
Right? That's the deal. So this
education system which was which was
meant to colonize us forever, it is now
keeping us mentally colonized. And it's
a great geopolitical tool. Sure. Indeed.
No question. to to keep us to keep us
down because the average person doesn't
know how to think.
And sometimes I get really frustrated
with the kind of questions I get. I've
been doing this for 4 years. I've been
talking about geopolitics for 4 years
and yet I get these questions that are
at the lowest like like the beginner
level. I understand there are new people
who come in but it it's sometimes you
know I get frustrated because I really
my objective is that you all will learn
something. you all will learn how to
think in a more nuanced manner. And
that's see that's the that's what
they've done to us. That is what they
have done to us. So the objective is to
keep us mediocre. That's the that's
exactly see this this here to keep us
mediocre. Exactly. It's to keep us
mediocre. The average Indian is super
mediocre. Sorry to say that. And that's
that's what frustrates me. We should not
be like this. We should not be like
this. We all have superior intelligence
but we have been programmed in such a
way that the the software that runs
inside is is is terrible. So we don't
know how to think and if somebody says
something contrary to what we've been
taught you all start forming and and
attacking that person. And that's how it
is. And that's why the ones the people
in India who have
the who actually see things and who want
a better life and who don't want a life
of mediocrity they automatically go to
the west that's how we have the brain
drain so it was a colonial tool which
has now been transformed into a
geopolitical tool and this the solution
to that is to reform the education
system but it looks like our leadership
is also super colonizing they don't see
the need for change in the education
system which is so so unfortunate I
would say so well thank you for asking
this question it's a very very relevant
question sir thank you so much
kaneshka says how can a vasal regain its
sovereignty with examples with examples
you want examples I well do I have
examples of a vasal regaining its
sovereignty
uh well the when when okay I'll give you
examples if you want a vasal to regain
its sovereignty the vasal needs to rid
itself of the overlord, right? Of the
oppressor.
Now, we could say that in 1947, we
regained our sovereignty. Did we really
regain our sovereignty? We are still,
like we just discussed, mentally
colonized. We are still mentally
colonized. Are we really sovereign from
that perspective? Are we once again a
civilization or are we still a nation
state? We are still a truncated entity.
We are still a nation state. We are not
a civilization state because of a
variety of reasons. I'll not go into
that. So how can a vasal regain its
sovereignty? One example is the British
islands under Rome, right? They were
colonized by Rome. The British islands,
England and Wales and Scotland, all of
these regions that we call today
England, Wales, Scotland, uh Ireland,
all of that was overrun by the Romans
for a few centuries. How did these
regions regain the sovereignty?
They regained the sovereignty
when the Roman Empire declined and
voluntarily left.
Until that happens, the only way you can
regain your sovereignty is by taking up
arms and expelling uh the occupiers. But
what if you're not occupied? What if
you're not under occupation? Then and
still a vasal like for example example
Pakistan. Pakistan is not under
occupation by the US or China but it is
still their vasal. So for that to happen
you have to get rid of the leadership
that is serving the foreigners for which
you will need maybe a revolution or
maybe something else.
Uh
okay let me just reiterate I will not
take questions that uh don't involve
geopolitics. I apologize to those of you
who may have put in money for this but I
have very clearly said and I beg you all
to pay attention.
I have it's in the title only
geopolitics and yet some people are
asking questions that are not about
geopolitics. Uh I apologize sincerely
but I will not take questions that are
not related to geopolitics. Sincere
apologies.
Uh
okay Jimmy Lee says uh given our
godgifted geographical location
shouldn't we be a naval superpower? What
is Bat's naval maritime history? Um we
should be the major maritime power one
of the top two or top three major
maritime powers in the world. No
question about it. The I mean look at
the geographical locations. Indians
don't understand this. You see the map
and TK Chah etc and all that. But look
at this from a strategic perspective. We
are halfway into the Indian Ocean all
the way down here. I mean there's no
nation with this kind of god-gifted
geographical location. We should be the
dominating maritime power in the region
with a maritime footprint all the way to
Antarctica, all the way to well the
shores of not the shores but the you
know
west of Australia, west of Indonesia. Uh
we should have nations all of East
Africa should should fall under our
purview. I mean we should have a naval
presence all the way there. We should,
right? But we don't. Our navy is is
decent. No no no question. I'm sure it's
pretty useful when it comes to if we
have to deal with Pakistan, even with
China. I'm sure I'm sure we have very
competent uh armed for naval personnel.
But look, why not have double the navy?
Why not have 100 submarines and and 300
warships? Why not 300 dedicated
warships? Not Coast Guard vessels and
all coast guard vessels. We should have
a thousand. Why not invest in that?
Right. But we but we haven't done that
and it takes time. The Chinese in 1990
were nowhere. They were a walkover. The
Americans could have defeated them in in
two days or maybe over a weekend. That's
how that's the kind of state the Chinese
Navy was in in 1990. And today it is the
numerically largest navy in the world.
And the Americans, you know, they they
see it as a major major threat which
could then become a Pacific threat.
So you have to invest in your navy. It
takes time. It takes a lot of effort. It
takes a lot of money. But if you want to
be a big deal, if you want to the world
to take yourself seriously, if you want
to be counted among the greats, if you
want to be genuinely sovereign, if you
want to ensure that your national
security is is, you know, that there are
no compromises with that, then you have
to invest in all the all these things. I
don't know what sort of leaders we've
had in the past, right? Today we we are
seeing changes. I'm glad to see that.
So, we should be a major naval power. I
don't like to use the word superpower
but I understand what you mean. What is
Bat's naval maritime history? Well, the
maritime history. What is the world's
oldest literature? Okay, let's not I
don't care what the west says. What is
actually the world's oldest literary
text? It is the riga, right? Must be
must have been written closer to 6,000
BC uh 6 yeah 6,000 BC then to 1500 BC.
Uh so in the Rigveda there are mentions
of ships
that sail on samudra and those ships
have 100 or oes or right those oes. So
this is one over this is another over
and ship that large you will have 50
guys on this side 50 guys on that side
all pulling the os and taking the ship
forward. The Romans used to have Roman
galleys warships. Okay, let me I'm sure
you must have seen them if you have
watched a movie like Benhur or any other
Roman themed movie. Okay, let's see. Uh
Roman galley
uh Roman galleys. So these are Roman
galleys. These were warships. Okay, this
is what it looked like. Take a look.
This is what it looked like. I mean, do
we have a larger picture? Come on, bro.
Uh let's let's embigen the picture.
Senatus populus kummanus spqr. So these
are Roman galleys. This is a model. So
the typical large Roman galley would
have a total of how many oes? 50 oes.
The oes were pulled by slaves who would
be below deck. They would be chained to
the ship. And if the ship goes down, the
slaves will go down with the ship.
That's how it was among the Romans
during the Roman era. So slaves would
pull the oes and there will be people
with lashes and whips who would ensure
that the slaves will do the job. So
these Roman warships had 50 oes in the
rigidic times. The rigid talks about
ships with a 100 oes. That tells you bat
has always had a glorious maritime
history. 5,000 years ago our people
reached Australia. There is undeniable
evidence of that. And you can't take a
aircraft to Australia 5,000 years ago.
you had to go by by sea by ship
and uh even of in more recent times I
mean let's talk about something that's
essentially day before yesterday for us
in our civilization context which is uh
the Chola era a thousand years ago uh
Rajendra and Raj Rajra Chola Rajar Chola
and his son Rajendra Chola Rajendra
Chola launched a maritime invasion of
Shiv Vijaya for because of a
geopolitical conflict and it was a
successful invasion I mean how far is
Shri Vijaya from here let's once again
go to the map my friends right from
southern India from the east coast of
India the invasion was launched and it
reached the shijaya so how far is that
right at least 2,000 kilometers imagine
taking a naval invasion fleet
India can't do that today we don't have
maritime co you know marine commandos we
have maros yes but we don't have
expeditionary forces we don't have
marines like The Americans have right
right
Chola had that he launched a maritime
invasion of Shivijaya and it was super
successful so we've had a glorious
maritime history but your teachers and
your textbooks won't teach you that your
teachers won't know about this because
they generally just memorize what the
textbooks tell them right
um so yes we should so this is where
history and geopolitics converge if you
understand the the historical context
then it tells why aren't we a great
naval power today we should be.
Abhinav says why does Azarbaijan support
Pakistan? Why should a conflict in the
Indian subcontinent even matter to them?
Any deeper reason or just because we
sell arms to Armenia? Well,
there's a religious reason to it.
Azarbaijan you could say is an extension
of Turkey, right? Uh they speak a
Turkish language, the Azeri language. Um
and and Turkey and Azarbaijan
essentially are working together
together to wipe Armenia off the face of
the earth ideally from their
perspective. You know that's their great
dream to create a pan corridor that
connects Turkey and Aabaijan with the
central Asian nations the Turk nations.
Once again let's go to the map so that
you get some context. I'm glad I'm able
to crack out the map a lot in this
episode. I enjoy that. So we're talking
about this region. So we have Turkey
over here. We have Armenia, this poor
little nation which was once a great
nation, great empire. And we have
Azarbaijan here. And uh so Azarbaijan is
a they are they speak a Turk language.
They're kind of Turk people. Turkey has
historically wanted to wipe out the
Armenians. They tried multiple times in
the late 19th century, early 20th
century, multiple waves of Armenian
genocides, which they still deny today.
And the Turks want to create a pan turan
corridor which connects Turkey,
erases Armenia off the map, connects
Turkey to Azarbaijan and connects that
that region to the rest of the central
Asian uh nations which are Turk speaking
nations. A pan turan corridor.
Uh and Turkey supports Pakistan very
strongly because of the Sunni angle and
because Tur Turkey has historically
hated India and so on. So Armenia kind
of goes along with Turkey and of course
India uh is in the process of it looks
like putting together an u you know an
anti-Turkey coalition uh Greece, Cyprus,
uh Armenia and so on. So the Turks kind
of feel the heat a little bit to some
extent at least right and that's why
Armenia goes along with whatever Turkey
tells them to do because they're an
extension of Turkey. They're anal of
Turkey and it also helps the US if all
of this happens. Uh so it's not just
because we sell arms to Armenia, it's
because of cultural, religious regions
reasons as well. Uh we will not take
non- geopolitical questions today. Let
me repeat that. Okay. I'll not take
questions about India's cities and
infrastructure and all that. Not today.
Okay.
Uh Ayat says, "Please say what the US is
exactly planning against me." Well,
that's for Mr. Trump to know. Mr. Trump
is very unhappy with you, sir. He
recently put out a very long uh post on
social media saying that you better you
should have actually thanked Mr. Trump.
Thank you very much, Mr. Trump. But you
are you are being you're not being very
very you're not showing sufficient
gratitude and he knew exactly where you
were when the whole thing was going on.
On the last day of the war, he had
Israel pull back its its fighter planes
which were going allegedly going to Iran
and so on. That's what he says. What is
Mr. Trump planning against you? I don't
think Mr. Trump is planning anything
against
I think Mr. Netanyahu may be planning
something. What what he's planning?
Well, only Mr. Netanyahu can tell us.
Okay. Uh Poll says, "Is Russia in the
condition to continue the war as Ukraine
is already running out of ammo and
people in the war? What's Russia's
condition?" Russia's condition is
perfectly fine. Uh I recently uh read
somewhere about a western assessment
about Russia's condition in the war and
they are perfectly hap perfectly
well uh uh perfectly capable of
continuing the war at least until 2027
without any issues. Russia they have
activated the war machinery they have
activated the military-industrial uh
complex all their factories are churning
out whatever needs to be churned out all
arms ammunition whatnot. They have uh um
supplies coming in from North Korea of
various kinds. They also have shahed
drones coming in from Iran and they may
also have now acquired the ability to
manufacture those shahed drones at home
in Russia. Russia is perfectly fine.
Russia is an author
they need. They don't need to depart
depend on anybody for imports of
anything. They are perfectly fine.
Ukraine it's it's look if the west
hadn't helped Ukraine with arms
ammunition and what not then Ukraine
would have already long ago capitulated.
So uh the west will keep this going as
far as I can see but but Russia is fine.
Okay. Uh once again let me remind you
I'm going to take only geopolitics
questions today. So let us not take
other questions.
Um,
Aayush says West's bias. Gaza ignored
Iran con condemned instantly. Well,
that's how it goes. The West does what?
It's it suit the it suits the West.
Uh, so once the Iran once the Israel
Iran conflict ended because of Mr.
Trump, uh, Gaza has started again by the
way in case you're not aware, but yeah,
that'll be ignored.
Um Agni Vana says why is Singapore not
sovereign? Well, if you look at
Singapore's history and look at the
Singapore's relationship with the US and
other countries, we'll understand why
it's not sovereign. U
and also because of the size of
Singapore, there's a lot of factors that
go into it. Okay, let's not take one.
There are only five sovereign nations.
The US, China, Russia, India, and
Israel. Apart from that, no nations are
fully sovereign. You have to understand
the treaties the nations have with
bigger powers. You need to understand
the relationship the nations have with
with bigger powers. If you want to
understand these things, you need to
take up my geopolitics course because
that's where I explain in detail.
Uh Abimman Gopinat says uh
what's
okay hypothetical question. If let I'm
not sure what is. Israel maybe
hypothetical. Why can't people just
write the whole thing? I know it's
typing or whatever. Uh if Israel and
Pakistan are hypothetically neighbors
and they go to war, who will win without
US interference since both have a good
army? Also imagining that Pakistan has
its own nuclear. Okay, imagine that
Pakistan has its own nuclear weapons
independent of the US. Uh both have good
armies and so on and both go to war. Uh
who will win if Isra and Pakistan are
both neighbors? Uh Pakistan is larger
than Israel. No question about that.
larger from a geographical perspective.
Um both are dependent on other nations
for fuel. So neither is u energ
self-sufficient from the perspective of
energy. Both have nukes. Imagining that
Pakistan has its own independent nuclear
arsenal. I would say Israel has a has
better technology. So if we take the
nuclear equation,
I would say Israel would defeat Pakistan
because of its superior technology
because they've done that in the past.
they fought all the Arab states at the
same time and defeated them in the past.
I would imagine that um even if the US
doesn't interfere u Israel may win.
Okay, as always let me remind you I will
take only geopolitics questions today.
Let me keep on reminding you people
because
Yeah. Okay. Let's take this one. Rohan
says, "As you have said, France is quasi
independent. Is Sweden also in the same
league?" No. No. Sweden is not. Sweden
is nowhere close to the quasi
independent status of France. Sweden is
fully vasalized.
Okay. Uh they were offered the F-35.
They refused to buy it. Look, they have
some autonomy. That's fine. They This
This is a subtle game that that is being
played. You have to keep keep the
illusion going that each country has its
own u
agency.
Okay?
And if the Swedish don't take the F-35,
they will make made to take something
else, but they will pay their dues.
Don't worry. And if Sweden doesn't take
the F-35, there's plenty of other F-35
clients in the EU in NATO, which is
fine. So just because Sweden opted not
to do something, it doesn't mean that
it's independent and sovereign.
Just look at the treaties that that
Sweden has signed. That's all you need
to do. But you have to do a little bit
of digging and research to understand
that.
I will not take religious questions
today. I will only this may be a super
chat question, super super chat episode,
but I will only take questions about
geopolitics. I mean it is in the pinned
comment. It is in the description of the
video. And yet people
I I don't get it.
I don't get is it not clear enough that
this is a geopolitics live stream? I
will not take non- geopolitics questions
even if you are taking a super chat.
Sorry.
Um
Sumit says, "How does the latest US
Supreme Court ruling regarding
injunctions from lower courts affect Mr.
Trump's agenda?" I haven't seen the sup
the Supreme Court ruling recent latest I
don't look at latest info latest news
look when you are a news reader you want
the latest Tazakar breaking breaking
breaking I don't do breaking stuff I
look at things from a geostrategic
perspective I look at what happened
let's say in the past week 10 days
ideally past 3 months 6 months and of
course I have a thousand year or
2,000year context window okay that
informs me about everything that is
relevant to a geopolitical situation and
then I look into the future so I don't
care about what happened in the in the
latest
uh injunction latest uh court ruling
eventually I will come to know about it
but I am not aware of it right now I'm
not aware of it but if you want since
you have asked this question and this is
kind of related to geopolitics let us
see let's try and see if I can pull
something out. Latest
US Supreme
Supreme Court ruling
Trump
uh Trump what's it say? Trump victorious
again. Supreme Court blocks judge's
power to block Trump's order in
birthright citizenship stuff. Giant win.
Okay, this is like 10, 20 hours ago, 6
hours ago and so on. It's a very recent
event. I haven't seen it. So, it looks
like Trump wanted to block. Let's see
what the Bibb has to say. Auntie Bibb
uh orders nationwide.
Okay, this is a domestic matter for the
US. Uh Trump's order to end birthright
citizenship for children of undocumented
immigrants and some temporary residents
and visitors and so on. So, I think it's
a victory for Trump Trump of some kind.
I'll not go and read the whole thing and
analyze it, but it looks like it's a
victory for Mr. Trump.
Uh so it's it's a boost for Mr. Trump's
agenda. Well, that's what I can say,
right? It's it's clearly a boost uh for
Mr. Trump's agenda. Now, somebody's
asking about men and girls, I mean, what
does it have to do with geopolitics?
I'll not take that question. Sorry. Um,
Sundesh says, "If at all World War II
happens between the US, NATO versus
Russia, China, Iran, North Korea, what's
the realistic possibility of India
staying neutral? If India is pulled into
the war, what who would do that? And
what's the post-war situation?" Let's
address the last question first. World
War II, postwar situation is a is a
stone age, a nuclear stone age with
radiation all over the place and with
maybe 10,000 people surviving on the
planet, humans possibly.
Yeah. 10 years down the line after the
war ends because World War II means a
nuclear war. I can't imagine the US and
NATO and all their vasals going to war
versus Russia, China. Forget Iran, North
Korea. Russia and China are the two two
nations that matter in this grouping. So
US and its minions that is NATO and
Japan and South Korea also okay all of
them versus Russia China they go to war.
So if that happens what's the realistic
possibility of India staying neutral? I
think there's a strong possibility of
India staying neutral. As long as China
doesn't bother India in this matter and
China doesn't try to uh change the
status quo, India will say we are
neutral. This is not our business. It's
not our war and the Americans will try
and pressurize India as much as
possible.
So that that is what the Americans will
do. Uh it is advantageous for China if
India stays out of it, right? Because if
India gets pulled into the war, India
will not be fighting with Russia and
China. India will be made to fight for
the US. That's what the US will want. Uh
so it is advantageous for China if India
is not pulled into the war. And it is
advantageous for us to not being be
pulled into the war. But let's say the
war happens and India stays out of it.
So I think there's a high probability
India will no matter what happens stay
out of it. Okay. Um if India is pulled
into the war, the Americans would do
that. They will apply some kind of
pressure which may force India. Okay.
But uh the highest possibility high
scenario a high probability 70 80% is
India stays neutral. Uh now um if World
War II happens there's a very very high
likelihood it goes nuclear which is the
end of the world because the Americans
have this doomsday scenario. Okay we
know about the Israeli Samson option. If
Israel is going under they will destroy
the entire neighborhood. They will
destroy all the Arab nations.
they will not go go down alone and they
have a list of targets that's already
pre-programmed
and as far as I know we are not part of
that because why would they want to nuke
us right when it comes to the Americans
they have their larger version of the of
the Samsung option so if America is in a
position where it is going to get nuked
by or or if it's in a position where
it's going to be defeated then they have
a doomsday contingency
in which they will launch nuclear
weapons at the entire world. So even if
India sits out, our cities will be nuked
by the Americans. You have no idea about
this, right? You all live in this such a
nice bubble. World is such a nice place.
If the Americans go down, they will take
the whole world down with them.
They will nuke the entire world. They
will even nuke India despite India never
having raised a single weapon against
the US. They will nuke everybody. So
that's your post-war situation, sir.
That's your postwar situation. There's
no there's no future.
Uh Prashant Prashant says, "What does
the NPT entail? How why and how did we
stay out the non-prololiferation
treaty?" I am not familiar with the
details of the nonprololiferation treaty
but it is a discriminatory discriminator
discriminatory treaty. So the NPT
non-prololiferation treaty it
essentially is is there to ensure I
don't remember the clause and the text
you can Google it that's fine but the
objective of this treaty is to ensure
that nuclear proliferation doesn't
happen so let's say there are let's say
hypothetically there are three nations
until the 1950s60s how many nations had
nuclear powers the US had nuclear
weapons uh the Russians had it China had
it France had it and the UK had
uh that's about it. Uh until the 1950s
and60s
uh so the objective of the NPT was to
ensure that other nations don't get
nuclear weapons. So the signatories up
to the treaty of the treaty were treaty
bound to not transfer nuclear technology
to other nations. Essentially that's
what it was. And the treaty then also
makes a difference between nations that
had nuclear weapons before 1960
something and nations that acquired
nuclear weapons after that date. And
those nations are are kind of uh given
secondass status or something. So it's a
discriminatory treaty
uh and it has this discriminatory uh
language and clauses and and
discriminatory treatment against nations
that became nuclear powers later. So we
became a nuclear power in 1974 which is
after their arbitrary completely
arbitrary cut off date. So there is
discriminatory treated treat treatment
against India even if we sign the treaty
and that's why we have chosen to stay
out of the NPT and if you wanted to look
at the details you can read up the the
the
language and the the the actual wording
of the treaty.
Uh
uh how geopolitically vital are you?
GBR greater than you. I'm not sure what
the question is but all right.
Um
media says geopolitical dub says media
says Putin and she aren't coming for the
bricks meeting. Okay. I don't know. Uh
I've heard that Mr. Shei is not coming.
Is Mr. Putin also not coming? Let's
let's quickly find out. I haven't heard
of it thus far. Okay. Bricks she is not
coming. I am I have heard about that.
So, bricks. Uh, she not coming.
Not bricks. What on earth?
Okay, it's my fault. It should be
bricks.
Not coming. Uh, Xinping pulls out. I'm
aware of Xiinping pulling out. PM Modi
invited for state dinner. PM Modi. So,
this is in Brazil. So, Xiinping is most
likely not coming. What about Putin?
Uh, bricks. submit Putin.
Putin will not go to blah blah blah.
Okay, there's an ICC arrest warrant
against him.
Well, that's interesting.
The core nations of bricks are the RAIC
nations. Russia, India, China, and
Russia is not coming. China is not
coming. Well,
okay. So be it. Mr. Mr. Putin is a valid
reason because the ICC, the
International Criminal Court, the
Americans hate, they have put on an
arrest warrant against Mr. Putin. So, it
makes sense for him to not come, right?
Uh Mr. Xi doesn't want to come. I don't
know why, but it's well, you know, there
are issues obviously
um that China has with
various countries. So, Mr. Xi has chosen
not to come. We're not sure quite sure
why, but whatever. So, it looks like
only Mr. Modi will be uh attending the
brick summit among the top three
nations. And then you have Brazil and
South Africa who will obviously be
represented by their heads of state.
Okay. Interesting.
Okay. Once again, I will not take non-
geopolitics questions. I will not take
non- geopolitics questions. It looks
like people simply don't follow the
rules.
Uh what can I say? What can I say?
Okay. Ready, always ready. when India
equals China and military like AI,
semiconductors, jets, submarines.
Um when will we have similar
technological capabilities? Maybe 10, 20
years. The Chinese started investing on
all this a long time ago. Before the
21st century, they were they already
identified the key uh engineering
sectors, the key technological areas
that they needed to be uh at par with
the US on and they started putting all
the components in place. they started
you know enhancing their education
system that academic system um their
academic system were they made sure it
focuses very strongly on on the science
uh and technology fields and they
ensured that the quality of the
university departments rises
significantly. They made sure they
attract global talent by giving them all
the facilities that you would want as a
researcher and all and the best possible
salaries you could imagine anywhere. So
they attracted the best talent and they
had all the technology slowly gradually
transferred to China and then they
started working on the technology and
enhancing the technology. So that's how
they did it step by step by step by
step. Today we are like we have woken
up. Okay, now we need this. Well, we are
what China was in the 1990s. It'll take
us at least 20 years I would say, right?
And we and our education system is
garbage comp. It's nothing comparable to
what China has. China's education system
was garbage in the 1990s, similar to
ours in some ways, but they invested
trillions of dollars into the education
system. Without reforming the education
system, you will not have a top quality
technological sector. You people I I
think the government doesn't seem to
realize that with third rate professors
who don't know how to do research, who
steal their students research, who force
their students to put their the
professor's name first in a research
paper. When you have this sort of
academic faculty all over the country,
not all but many,
well then what research output will the
country have? When you have government
labs where you are paid those little
salaries, little salaries, but if you
are good enough, you can go to the US
and have a salary of hundreds of
thousands of dollars a year. I mean, who
will stay in India? Tell me. Well, we
have these self-imposed problems. So,
it's going to take us a long time to
equal China. long time.
Vive Singh says France didn't give us
meteor. Is this a question or a
statement
meteor? I think we haven't
I'm not aware. Not aware.
Okay. Now, what is this? Joseph Chhatria
says, "If Israel controls the US, then
why they have F-35 instead of F-32?"
F-22. Well, that's a good question. The
US seems to have summer. Look,
there's always the question of who is
the master, who is the vasal. Some say
the US is the master and Israel is the
vasal. Others say that Israel is the
master and the US is the vasal. Well,
imagine hypothetically that that Israel
is the master and the US is the vasal.
Hypothetically, well, even that even in
that case, it doesn't mean Israel
controls every goddamn thing that
happens to the US. The US will still
have some autonomy, right? They're very
they are the most powerful nation. So
right I don't know have any opinion on
the Jesuit orders and this is not a
geopolitical question.
Rashi Kudin says, "What are who are
India's biggest non-s superpower threats
and why?" Well, the superpower obviously
non non-s superpower threats. Oh, it's
obvious. Look at look at the map. Look
at the map. I mean, let me put the map
on the screen and let's let's walk walk
through this.
Who are our biggest non-s superpower
threats? So, the obvious threats are
right here on the map, aren't they?
First of all, Pakistan is a threat.
North of India, we have Chinese occupies
Tibet. So, so China is a threat. Then
you have East Pakistan which is a vasal
of the US now, newly minted vasal and
it's also dallying with China. That is
well it's it's it's a problem. It's not
really a threat but it's a problem
because of the illegal infiltration
issue. Then you have a civil war issue
in Myanmar because of which there are
millions of god knows what kind of
people coming into u into India and
that's messed up things. So but that is
the superpower threat because the civil
war is is being orchestrated by the US.
So obviously the threats over here are
China, Pakistan, Bangladesh is an issue,
right? Apart from that we have non-s
superpower threats in the in the forms
of various uh embedded threats within
India which are proxies of the
superpower which are a variety of NOS's
variety of reg religious organizations
and so much more. Uh who else? Turkey is
kind of an adversary of India. You have
various European nations that are very
very poorly inclined towards India. I'm
not naming anybody here. Okay? Uh but if
you look at uh because they are all
extensions of the superpower
uh and so on. So there are various state
threats, there are various non-state
threats that all go back to a particular
state because they are proxies and
that's the deal. Uh
Chundra, thank you so much. Thank you G.
Thank you. Um
Ayatah Kamehamehi says, "What role can I
play in India's strategy to bypass
Pakistan and access Afghanistan and
Central Asia through Shabbah port? Can I
defeat Israel?" Uh Iran is not in a
position to defeat Israel right now. I
mean you can but then it'll bring out
the Israeli Samson option. So I I'm
pretty sure that Iran seems to, as far
as I understand, seems to have more
ballistic and cruise missiles than uh
Israel's Iron Dome missiles, which means
that eventually Israel's Iron Dome may
run out. It may run out of missiles. It
will have no more missiles to uh to to
intercept the incoming ballistic
missiles. At that point in time, it
becomes a numerical certainty that
Iranian ballistic missiles and crew
missiles will hit the targets in Israel.
So that's a problem. So yeah um that can
happen but to defeat Israel you have to
actually move into Israel that that's
not possible right so it's not possible
for Iran to actually defeat Isra is
especially considering the fact that the
US stands behind Israel so Iran cannot
defeat Israel the only thing Iran can do
is remain sovereign that's the best
possible option now what role can you
play in Iran's India's strategy to
bypass Pakistan access Afghanistan and
central Asia through Jabahar portur well
the role that you're playing is the role
you can play no other role. So here's
the deal. Let's go to the map.
Let's open the map. And so we have
Chabahar port here. Okay, this is
Chabahar here.
Uh it's in Iran and Balojasthan.
And through this port so India can can
send shipments of various goods etc.
from uh the west coast of India from
maybe Gujarat from maybe Maharashtra
etc. send consignments to Chabahar then
the consignments will be taken over land
into Afghanistan to supply Afghanistan
with whatever Afghanistan needs because
Pakistan is blocking access to
Afghanistan. So we have to go through
Iran. Um and similarly we can also
access Central Asia through once we
reach Chabahar we can go through Iran
and access various parts of Central
Asia. So that's what Iran is doing and
one we appreciate that. So that's why
Iran is is indeed important for India.
Uh I will only take geopolitical
questions. I think people just don't get
it right.
Okay. Uh no point getting frustrated.
People won't change.
Um now this this is the best
geopolitical question today I would say.
Why did the NATO chief called Trump
daddy? I I don't know.
I don't know. Uh okay, now this is a
good question. See, this is this is a
good question.
I I would like to see questions at least
of this this caliber. Okay, so
Vadi Yan Nirby says, "Well, thank you
for being a big fan. Thank you. uh how
does the US vasalize other nations and
why has hasn't India been vasalized by
the US till now see the Americans have
hidden their instruments of power
they're very smart historically great
empires would show off would display
their means of power so everybody could
see the scary stuff but today the whole
world has been taken over by the
Americans but you don't see what makes
the Americans so dangerous and scary you
don't see how they can wipe out and
flatten a country at 30 minutes notice.
Everything has been hidden away. Only
the ones who are in power in a nation
will know and understand the threat. Uh
so now the question is how does the US
vasel how has it historically vasalized
other nations? One way of doing it is
through treaties.
a treaty a mutual self-defense treaty
which becomes a military treaty and it
has clauses that can that will make the
nation the other nation dependent of the
US and if you can have a clause in which
you can have military bases on the on
the nation that vasalizes the nation and
the the language of the treaty can
vasalize a nation because it it imposes
certain sovereignty limitations on the
nation. The NATO treaty is one such
treaty which takes away
uh military sovereignty from the NATO
states but it offers protection. So it's
like you know I'm a big gunda
and you cannot have any weapons in your
house but I'll protect you. You're going
to pay that sort of thing. Uh then there
is economic sovereignty taken away by
the EU treaty. You become a member of
the EU. You give away a lot of your
sovereignty, decision-m power, policy
phrasing power, all of that. So there
are so many ways in which the US does
it. So it uses treaties to a very large
extent and the treaties are underwritten
by the American military strength. So if
you if you sign the treaty and then you
don't
uh when you don't obey the treaty then
the Americans will they can enforce the
treaty they can enforce it and they have
the means to do that military means.
Then you have other forms of
vasalization like what you see in Japan
in South Korea which is military
occupation. U another way of vasalizing
a country is by writing the country's so
constitution and by making that the
constitution very uh pacifistic
and changing and and and shaping the
country's education system what's been
done to Japan. So older Japanese people
they are they they they are super
pacifistic people they hate violence
which means that they hate the military.
They don't want Japan to have a
military. They that's been ingrained
into them mentally. They've been
brainwashed and so on. So there are so
many ways of vasalizing a nation. It
takes time and so on.
JMA says prospects of AMC advanced
medium combat aircraft MRFA uh compared
to other fifth generation fighter
planes. AMC look at the end of the day
it all depends on the on the jet engine.
The Achilles heel is the jet engine. As
long as we depend on the US or any other
nation for jet engines, h no prospects.
We can design the best aircraft body and
systems and everything, but if we don't
own the jet engine, there's no
prospects. So that is what we need to to
do. Otherwise, I think that the AMCA
will have its first prototype coming out
in a year or two and the first test
flight in in the next two or three years
and it's supposed to begin uh initial
production by 2030, 2031 or something
like that.
uh MRFA well multi-roll fighter aircraft
I'm not sure what that is there are lots
of MRFAS multiroll fighter aircraft
aircraft but AMC I can tell you yeah
Agni Varna says what are Switzerland's
geopolitical concerns it's a tiny nation
surrounded by so many bigger powers
that's there itself is the geopolitical
concern right
there itself
um Rishiesh says
Did the Plaza Accords stagnate Japan's
economy? If Japan had not signed it,
would it have would they have surpassed
Uncle Sam? In the 1980s, I was a little
kid. And the world looked at Japan with
awe. Japan, this tiny little nation, was
the world's second largest economy. And
it looked like it was just a matter of
time before they became the largest
economy. Right? And then the Plaza
Accords happened. I was 85 or something.
And then slowly gradually the tap got
turned and Japan slowly slid into
decline.
So the it was the Plaza Accords that
stagnated Japan's economy and the
instrument that was used to do this was
the Bank of Japan. And I'll not go into
the details but if the Plaza Accord has
not had not happened they would have
surpassed Uncle Sam. But Japan had no
choice sign or not sign. Who the hell
were the Japanese to say no to to the
nation that had more than 130 permanent
U military bases on their territory? You
can't say no to your occupier. So yeah,
uh Rohan Suna says, "Is Ukraine being
trapped into in a new version of the
Lendley's act?" Okay, you're talking
about the Second World War. Like in the
Second World War, uh the UK and USSR got
US equipment and the last repayment was
made in 2006 after 61 years.
Yes, Ukraine is being trapped like that.
It's going to be forever indebted to
Uncle Sam and to various NATO nations
and maybe the EU nations. Ukraine is
done. It is cooked.
Yeah. They've lost the flower of their
youth. They've lost all their young men.
They only have old men left. Even women
are being sent to the front lines to to
fight. And uh their economy has been
destroyed. They've they've signed this
minerals deal with the US which further
vasalizes Ukraine and yeah so the
analogy that you have given is pretty
apt. Yes.
Ash Dar says what's the strategy to get
aarat in a 100 years.
The strategy first of all is for India
to grow grow grow grow grow economically
become a $30 trillion economy eventually
a $50 trillion economy eventually a
hundred trill trillion dollar economy if
possible in a 100 years absolutely
possible and the trick is to ensure we
don't get embroiled in any major
military conflict which is easier said
than done if you do that the simple fact
of India's gigantic economy with which
comes a gigantic military strength it
itself will ensure that the rest of the
countries in Akan bharat
will simply automatically come in.
That's the only strategy. The larger you
become economically, the more powerful
you get militarily and power is like a
pressure that goes outwards
and once you have a gigantically
powerful nation,
everything just falls into place. You
don't have to do a thing. So that's why
India should not be hasty. Oh.
Wait, relax, work, do the hard work. Now
everything will come automatically.
Sesh uh has a recommendation. Instead of
sixth generation air superiority, we
should quietly focus on space attack
cost effective and future ready where
the true adv war advantage lies. I think
it's a good suggestion. What are my
views on this? Um I am in I am very much
in favor of a space force, a powerful
space force. Um we have various treaties
apparently that say that space should
not be militarized. Well, nobody cares
about treaties.
Um the US already has a space force,
right? Trump had created a space force
during his first uh tenure as president.
Uh we should definitely focus on space
capabilities.
We should not term them as military
capabilities. we should term them as as
civilian capabilities. But the very fact
that you can put up rockets and
satellites in space, lots of them. The
very fact that you can put up space
stations in space always all of these
things have dual uh uses which uh dual
uses in civilian and military use.
Right? So we should do do that. We
certainly should do that. Which is why I
keep on saying that ISRO needs to be
more ambitious. And what I mean byro
should be more ambitious means the
government should be more ambitious for
ISRO. ISRO has no decision-making power.
They only take orders and execute the
orders.
They have limited budgets and so on. So
um ISRO
should be unleashed.
IshRO should ISRO should be allowed to
uh you know design and build rockets
that are like 100 times more powerful
than what we have today. Our rockets are
mediocre little rockets. The PSLV and
the LM3 they what are they compared to
the space SpaceX rockets? a fraction of
of what the SpaceX rockets can do. So we
should focus on all of these things for
sure. At the same time we should also
focus on all the other landbased
technologies and sea based technologies
and atmospheric air based technologies.
We should not solely focus on something
on one thing. We should focus on
everything. But uh if we truly want to
stand out among the nations and ensure
that our national interests are served
long term we have to become a
technological superpower. No question.
Um Prashant says, "Did Israel mess
Trump's quest for a Nobel Prize?" Hence
angry. Did Israel do that?
Um
so Israel has u abided by the ceasefire,
hasn't it?
Um
Trump said that I have uh mediated uh
mediated a ceasefire. The ceasefire is
now in effect. And then Israel did try
to breach the ceasefire. Trump was angry
and he was pretty frustrated on camera.
He said he used language that you a
president would generally not use on
camera, but he did that. He was pretty
annoyed, pretty frustrated, and he
singled out Israel for this, not Iran.
He singled out Israel for that. even put
uh these angry
uh posts on truth social mentioning
Israel. So Israel was trying to kind of
get away with a few things but Trump was
angry but the ceasefire is holding and
if it holds and the war is over it means
that Trump has actually succeeded in
achieving peace. So he was angry at the
time but now Israel seems to you know
seems to be abiding by the se with by
the ceasefire. So yeah, Trump may
actually get Nobel Prize for this, you
know.
Um,
how does Turkey develop? How
how did Turkey develop great drones in
aircraft which are fifth generation?
Through research and development.
So they have this drone company by Rakar
or whatever it's called. They have the
Kizilma drone which is a stealth capable
drone.
Not sure if it's a fifth generation
drone or something aircraft. Okay, we're
talking about drones first. So, uh the
the the Baktar or whatever the company
is called.
It was um the guy behind it is uh is a
guy who was doing an engineering degree,
PhD or something in the US and then he
got got the idea for this this uh drone
thing and he abandoned his degree and
came back to Turkey and his dad has a
had a big uh operation already going
some kind of industrial operation. So he
tapped into that and formed this company
and yeah, so that's the company that
produces all these drones. I'm not sure
how great the drones are because the
drones came up against us during
Operation Synindur and we took them all
out, but it doesn't mean that Pakistan
had the best drones that Turkey has to
offer. Okay, so they may have high
quality drones still, but the reputation
has taken a big tumble.
Um, so how do you do it? You do it by
research and development, iterative
research and development. That's how you
do it. So Turkey did it. We also can do
it if we create the right environment in
India, right? So yeah, when's the next
super chart? We'll see.
Um
what?
Yeah, this is not a geopolitics
question.
Okay.
I mean, this sounds like a geopolitics
question, but then you're putting in
Doctor Strange and Marvel, which is
cinema.
How is this geopolitics? Doctor Strange
is fiction. It's it's fantasy.
Amaya Rupal says, "Soner or later, China
will get entangled in the Taiwan
takeover war." Are you sure about that?
How do you know that? You're assuming
this to be to be a fact. How do you know
that? Yes.
Okay. Anyway, let's take this.
So, sooner or later,
China will get entangled in Taiwan take
over war. That will present us with a
chance for action in Axai Chin. How
should India prepare for the scenario?
My thoughts. My thoughts. If China goes
to war with Taiwan, we should not go for
a chin. Okay.
We should not.
not the time China is still very
powerful uh of course it if if it is
see it's like this if China does make a
move on Taiwan if it does okay I'm not
saying it is guaranteed to do it anytime
soon or whatever but let's say
hypothetically it does if China does
that we should actually seek to ensure
the safety and security of Nepal and
Bhutan
it doesn't mean I'm I'm not recommending
we should physically take over these
nations. I'm saying we should be on very
high alert and ensure that Chinese China
doesn't make any moves in Nepal or
Bhutan. If China faces a significant
defeat
in Taiwan, then they will be forced to
divert other forces to Taiwan, which may
present us with an opportunity to take
over Axachin. And then the question is
if we do take over axin or take over
some parts of it and then when the
Taiwan war ends if what if China is
still in a position to uh engage us
militarily. So it's something that you
know you have to be very careful about.
We can discuss all these things
hypothetically theoretically but in the
real world there are real world
consequences for actions. Uh so it so if
China gets entangled in Taiwan it does
not necessarily present us with a chance
for action for action.
What action
right? So it doesn't necessarily present
us with a chance for taking over excite
chain. We have to be patient. Ask
yourself this very simple question. Are
we as big as China? Strong as China.
We're not. China is about two and a half
times more powerful than us.
So as a weaker nation do we genuinely
deserve to take back our territories
that we have lost? We will deserve it
when we are strong enough to take it.
But right now we are weak. Please
understand Indians seem to be imagining
that we are one step away from being a
superpower.
Okay.
Prrenumar says system needs to work for
us in India we work for it. Okay. Okay,
this is not a geopolitics question. I
just don't get it. Why people?
Okay.
Okay. Prabhav says, "Why Russia still
chooses a slow conventional war instead
of a decisive one? And similarly, Israel
doesn't wage a decisive war against
Iran."
Um,
that's a good question. Why has Russia
chosen I mean Russia when the the
Ukraine war began? Uh it began in
February 2022.
A couple of a few weeks after the war
began, Russia's Russian troops were on
the outskirts of Kiev
and then they withdrew from that and
then after that they've chosen a slow
conventional war.
So maybe they want to not risk not take
big risks because uh a very quick rapid
crushing defeat of Ukraine will involve
the air force. It may end up uh
demonstrating its air force
capabilities, Russia's air force
capabilities to NATO. Um Russia has made
it very made it a point to keep the air
force out of action as far as possible.
They have a very powerful, very big air
force, but a very little of that has
been used over Ukraine. Um, so I think
there are considerations that they want
to extend this as long as possible to
deplete
NATO's resources. Forget about Ukraine,
but NATO's resources and and create this
this fatigue in the world for the
Ukraine war. The world should be fed up
of the Ukraine war. and then Russia can
essentially you know get what it wants
to achieve without uh risking too much
probably that's the cause Israel doesn't
wage a decisive war against Iran do you
know that there's a thousand kilometers
diff
you know distance there's a distance of
about 1,000 km between Israel and Iran
it's like
imagine you want to wage a war with for
example hypothetically South Korea
I mean, think about it.
It's far away, right? How do you do it?
So, there are geographical reasons for
all this, right?
Okay. Jinny says, uh, do you think
Russia was given Ukraine by the by us,
by the US
to not interfere in Iran?
Russia was given Ukraine. Who has given
Russia Ukraine?
I'm I'm trying to understand what the
question is. Do you think Russia was
given Ukraine by us? Maybe you mean US.
So, has Russia been given Ukraine by the
US?
Has it?
It's not.
So, I'm I'm not I'm really not sure what
you're asking. What new wars do I see
will start in coming years or months?
Well, for that you have to look at the
global flash points right now. You know
where are the areas of maximum tension.
One is India Pakistan. You could have a
war next week. Who knows if Pakistan
does some something stupid, right? We
know that. So that could happen anytime
depending on Pakistani activities and
actions because they are a terrorist
nation and you terrorists don't really
think too much, right? They just do
stupid things, terrible things. So if if
there's a terrorist attack somewhere in
India then well Pakistan will will you
know it'll they'll have it coming. So
that's one flash point. Another flash
point is India, China. Right now we have
the Kailash manser yatra going on. The
Chinese pretending pretending to be very
nice while imposing sanctions on India
of various kinds, right? Uh fertilizer
sanctions, rare earth magnets sanctions,
other sanctions. Uh so India, China is
always a flash point. Then there is
Taiwan which is a flash point. Then
obviously Ukraine is is an ongoing flash
point. So I think what new wars could
happen? uh there are wars happening in
Africa also that nobody pays attention
to. So that is already going on.
So I think China Taiwan is an is is a
potential flash point. India Pakistan is
a potential flash point. Uh an
escalation of the Ukraine war is a
potential flash point. Israel Iran
blowing up again is also a potential
flash point. That's what I can think of.
North Korea seems, you know, the West
portrays North Korea as a crazy nation,
but it's not really a crazy nation. is a
very sane rational nation and so on. So
I think that's that's an overview of
what could potentially happen.
Okay. Suhak Deepak says, "Thank you so
much for being a big fan, sir. Uh RPM
record visits to the different nations.
When do you see dividends coming in in
what form?" See, diplomacy is all soft
and dividends can come in a variety of
ways. You go and visit a nation and and
two years later in a UN vote they may
because you have established good
relations with them they may give a vote
in your favor.
So in a UN vote the nation votes on in
your favor that's a dividend but most
people won't see it and they'll say
that's what people that's how people
react.
The dividends come in so many different
ways and means and shapes and forms.
They may for example have various maybe
an Indian Indian private company take
over a port in their nation or maybe
build infrastructure in the nation. When
a company builds a port in in a
different nation or builds
infrastructure in a in a third nation,
it's not a public facing thing. So
people never come to know about this
what's happening and even if somebody
reports it they'll say what is that
what's the point but that has
geopolitical implications. So there are
lots and lots of different dividends
that come in a variety of shapes and
forms but most people because they don't
understand geopolitics geostrategy they
don't see it they don't understand it.
So you have to pay attention to the to
the uh things that really matter. You
have to pay attention to supply chains
and supply chains means you have to pay
attention to the hubs and spokes of
supply chains uh ports, airports,
railway lines, uh transport corridors,
uh infrastructure building. You need to
look into that. Then you you have to
look at uh the voting patterns of
nations in in in multilateral
organizations. Those are dividends. And
there are so many other dividends. Your
trade agreement, people don't understand
trade agreements or a trade deal.
It's very complicated, so much
paperwork, but that's dividends. There
are so many different ways all of these
things pays dividends. You may you may
get oil, for example, let's say the
prevailing rate is $75 per barrel. You
may get it at $70 per barrel. That's a
dividend. But nobody will get it, right?
That okay, they reduce the for India uh
$5 per barrel.
So there are so many ways in which these
these these visits of the prime minister
across the world they pay dividends but
because our education system doesn't
teach us these nuances we don't get it
right so I hope that that sheds some
light on the matter
uh K says how can India deal with a
future destabilized Pakistan their
population is doubling that economy is
not averaging given 2% growth. Okay,
that's a good question. Pakistan is an
unstable nation. De destabilization is
always the case with Pakistan, right? Um
there are all kinds of, you know, civil
war issues in Pakistan. All kinds of
insurgencies, many separatist movements,
you know, independence movements and uh
regions and nations that want freedom
from Pakistan, whether it is Kibber
Pakuna, whether it is Baljustan, whoever
else and so on. and a very radicalized
population of very very ill-educated
their education system is even worse
than ours if that if that's possible. So
people who can't think straight h people
who lack the ability to to think
critically but even worse than Indians
like significantly worse than Indians
and completely mentally radicalized like
crazies most of them not all of them
some I I know that there are some good
people also in Pakistan but most of them
are like this right
so Pakistan if it becomes even more
destabilized than it is right now then
there is obviously the potential for
trouble for India so how do we deal with
this look very simple secure the borders
That's it. Ensure nobody crosses the
borders. You cross that line, you're
done, bro. That should be the very clear
and simple message to all Pakistanis.
You guys, we gave you a nation. As long
as we don't retake it, it's yours. Okay?
Temporarily, it's yours. But as long as
you are a separate nation and there is
there are these lines on the map, you
better not cross cross those lines. the
moment you come on the side illegally
and because we have we don't want you
here it's illegal you're done that's it
that's what we have to ensure
uh manticor says do you think India has
a large source or reserves of rare
earths um that's an important question
and this is geopolitical this is a g
geopolitical question even though it did
it's related to India's rare earth
reserves but see what's happened right
now is that China is imposing
restrictions on rare earth exports which
is directly impacting India's electric
vehicles uh vehicles industry India's uh
battery manufacturing industries and all
and it looks like by mid July we may run
out of what we need the the resources
the rare earths it's which are coming
from China and China has imposed
sanctions on India when it comes to rare
earth magnets also when it comes to uh
specialty fertilizers and so much more
so China is imposing sanctions on India
which is why it's very important that we
diversify our sources of these very
vital uh resources rare earths now the
question is do I think India is has a
large
res reserves of of rare earths as far as
I know India is the third largest has
the world's third largest reserves of
rare earths but we have never developed
the industrial capabilities to extract
to a extract the rare earths and b
purify and process them and that's why
we are dependent on others we have
everything in India
we have it
but we have been utterly lazy
we have been caught napping even this
current government has been caught
napping they have been here in power for
11 years why haven't they developed the
capabilities to to uh extract rare
earths and then process them and purify
them why hasn't it been done thus
I don't get it. This is the L.
Okay,
you got to say it.
Uh, so India, I think, has the world's
third largest reserves of rare earths. I
I don't know why we haven't done it. I I
think only the government needs to
answer the question, not me. Um, lithium
in Jammu and Kashmir, that's been
announced. But what's been done? It's
been announced a year ago. What action
has been taken to start the extraction
of this lithium? We're still talking to
Brazil and god knows what for lithium
and whatn not. If we have discovered
lithium in Jammu, Kashmir and other
places, why aren't we hard at work
already extracting it or setting up the
infrastructure for extracting and
purifying it? Why hasn't it happened?
Why does everything take so long,
decades in this country?
Whose failure is it? Is it Manm Singh's
failure?
Well, Manm Singh was in power until
2014, right? I think we need to move
faster.
We need to move faster. This is
constructive criticism really.
Okay. Shubam
Kumbakar says, "Given India's internal
diversity and cultural links with our
neighbors, why haven't we built a deep
intel network to secure influence and
strategic leverage?
Okay.
Why haven't we built this deep intel
network? Well, my question to you sir is
how do we know we haven't built it? When
you build intelligence networks, do you
think you announce them to the world?
Okay. Today in Pakistan we have
established three more spy operations
agencies uh locations and one is in
Rahul Pindi, one is in Islamabad, one is
in Queta and in the next 3 months we
will establish five more outposts.
First out outpost will be in Guadada,
second outpost will be in whatever else
place and so on so do you think that's
how it works? Do you think that's how we
do it? If we build these deep intel
networks, do you think we we we spell it
out, we announce it, it's never supposed
to be known.
Okay. So, because this is this doesn't
this doesn't come in the news, it
doesn't come in government reports,
doesn't mean it doesn't exist,
right? So, that's that's the answer. My
answer is this question that I pose to
you.
Okay?
Yeah, I will only take geopolitics
questions and um
okay let's take this uh anyone loyal to
Bhat was eliminated. Bhagat Singh,
Chandra Shakar Razad, Subash Bose, later
Hobie Baba is scientists
PM Modi is still there. Okay. So if
you're not dead, if you're not dead, you
must have kissed the ring. Is that is
that so? He has has he kissed the ring
in pushing US deep state agenda GMO
agriculture arms.
India is refusing to allow US
agricultural exports into India. That's
one of the big issues when it comes to
the trade talks. Trump wants India
to allow the US to export their
agriculture products into India, their
genetically modified garbage into India,
their dairy products into India. Then
Indians will start becoming obese like
the Americans. We are saying no. Right?
The US is all powerful.
See this is the problem in India. People
don't understand nuance.
So has Mr. I'll just answer this
straight away instead of going into
nuances and details and all. Has Mr.
Modi kissed the ring? He has not kissed
the ring. He's fighting as hard as is
possible. I mean going up against Trump
and telling him he's a liar on his face
by putting out the statement after the
G7 summit. I mean is that an example of
somebody kissing the ring? I mean
seriously
it's not your fault Shir Patra it's the
education system's fault which has not
taught our people how to think
in nuances think critically.
You see these patterns that various
great YouTubers will give you
Indian YouTubers and then you say yeah
this is the pattern and that means that
Prime Minister Modi is working for the
US. Oh, are you kidding me?
Prime Minister Modi despite not having a
full majority is doing all he can to
keep India sovereign. He's even he has
even essentially taken the step of
calling Trump a liar because Trump lied.
He's taking big risks and you people are
saying has Mr. Modi is the are you
kidding me?
I just now criticized the government
right about rare earths. So I am very
clear that I will criticize when
criticism is required.
We haven't done a thing about rare
earths. We announced lithium in Jammu
and Kashmir more than a year ago. What
happened?
So I will criticize the government where
it deserves to be criticized. But this
is nonsense.
This is nonsense. Mr. Modi is working
for India. He's taking big risks for
India. So
okay. Uh Mantacor says, "Is it high time
we make mandatory participation of IITs
in I R&D projects like the US and China?
Should we enforce this to strict levels
to enforce compliance?"
Well, that's a that's a good um that's a
good uh reformative step you you're
talking about. The first thing we need
to do in IIT is is shut down the
godamned non
science and technology departments.
Why do we have see these are the Indian
institutes of what? what technology
Indian institutes of technology right so
why do you have sociology departments in
IITs why do we have these nonscience
non-technology departments in IIT where
a significant portion of the budget of
the IIT goes why do we have these things
there and these are all leftist snake
pits see the kind of garbage research
they are peddling
third rate researchers
who who don't contribute a thing to the
nation
the leech from the nation. I mean once I
get started about this I will not
uh so yes the IT should
they should be more research focused cut
off this you know trim out all this fat
get rid of all the sociology and all
these humanities departments from the
IITs I don't understand why they exist
there are some good people also in these
IITs okay in the humanities departments
there are some good people
no question and when this happens
they'll this may end up you
being bad for them. For example, Dr.
Suri Prakashya, which whom I did with
with whom I did a podcast on this
channel. He's from IIT Mandi.
He's a great guy. He's a patriot.
But yeah, but most of these academics in
these humanities departments, they most
of them, not all of them, most of them
are parasites.
And all of this IIT funding, much of it
is going into these departments. So
that's one issue with IITs. Okay. And
then of course R&D, you need more R&D.
If you look at the quality of research
in IIT, well,
it's nothing to write home about. If you
go to the average IIT, I'm not saying
all I there may be some super
exceptional IIT somewhere. You go to the
average IIT H, you'll find if you go to
the washroom, it's a milliondoll
washroom.
Beautiful. If you go to the presentation
room, you know, um the lecture uh
what is it called a room um lecture hall
or whatever
it it will be very well equipped and all
that. But if you so if you go to the
washroom it will they will have they
will have spent crores on the washrooms.
If you go to the presentation rooms and
all that they will have spent crores on
that. But if you go to the laboratories
and you see the equipment there, the
equipments are 20 30 years old. If you
look at the professors,
you'll find that most of them are
utterly mediocre.
And they produce lots of research papers
every year. And how do they produce
these research papers? They have their
the students they are supervising do all
the research and then they will put
their name as the first author in the
research paper and the students have to
agree with agree to do this otherwise
they will not get their PhDs or
whatever. This is the deal. I'm not
saying all I professors are like that
but there is a big issue about all of
these issues about all of these problems
in IIT in the IITs. So very uh
tremendous amounts of mediocrity.
Okay. So a lot needs to be changed and
here more R&D projects actual R&D where
if you don't R&D you you it's it's sink
or swim. You're thrown out otherwise and
you to do it yourself. No don't have
your students do everything for you. So
a lot needs to be done.
Mr. Adriata says do the people of
Axachin still have allegiance to India?
Okay, let's let's let me show you
something. Okay, we'll go to the map.
We will go to the map. Yes,
this is something you all can also do. I
mean I I encourage you all my viewers to
sometimes do some research yourselves.
See exactly what I'm doing. Okay, I
don't need you to solve the Schinger
equation. Just look at this. This is
excit.
Now look here. This is Ladak, Kashmir.
You can see there is Kard here. There is
Shagar here. There is Lei here. There's
Cargill. You can see all the cities. You
can see all the towns. Hund is a
wonderful place. Diskit is a wonderful
place. Turuk is Yeah.
And there is Tang the last village and
so on. You can see all the towns,
villages when you look at the map. Now
let's look at Axai.
Show me a village here.
Show me a town here. Show me
the Show me.
Show me. Is there any town here? Is
there any village here?
Show me where is it?
Where is it?
So you can answer your own question by
just doing what I just did. The answer
to your question is
the people of Akaiin
have no allegiance to India.
Why is that? Because there are no people
who live in Axachin.
Okay.
Ankita Krup says war and conflicts are
necessary for the sustenance of the US
economy and to maintain the US dollar as
the international currency. Uh what's
the reality of the US economy? Who is
next after Iran? The reality of the US
economy is that the entire US economy is
a scam. It is based on a currency that
has no actual value. The only value that
the currency has is the might of the US
global power military power production
capability.
Uh and that keeps this paper currency
uh going on as the global reserve
currency.
Why do I say this currency has no value?
Because a currency needs to be a
substitute for something which has
value. Historically
currencies were in the form of coins,
gold coins. So the gold itself had
tremendous value, right? So that's how
currencies had value. Then eventually
you started issuing paper currencies.
But there was a promise made on the
paper currency written down that this
currency is legal. It's it's legally
exchangeable for so and so amount of
gold and if and this is legal tender for
that and if the bearer demands that
amount of gold then the bank or the
government has to issue that amount of
gold in exchange for that piece of
paper. That's how it was. So that's how
you knew that this and that the
government had to keep that amount of
gold in reserve the amount of currency
notes that it had issued. So that's how
we know that the currency has some
actual value or what what actual value
the currency has. So historically in
India our currencies were either gold or
silver.
Now the dollar is for some time it was
linked to petroleum. It was called the
petro dollar. Now it's not even that.
It's simply a worthless piece of paper.
But it is the the American military
might is enforcing uh the continuing uh
continuation of the US dollar as the
global reserve currency. Uh so that's
the reality of the US economy. The US
economy the the US has the most debt of
any nation on the planet. How is this
debt? What is debt? So the US borrows
dollars from other countries. Dollars
that are in circulation across the
world. How do they borrow the dollars?
They borrow the dollars by by issuing
bonds.
So a bond maybe of $100. If if you buy a
100 bonds of $100 each, that's $10,000.
So what the government, US government
does, it issues these bonds that you can
buy.
So you let's say one bond hypothetically
is is worth $100 and you buy a hundred
of those then you have to pay $10,000
and a bond will eventually be something
that matures which means that you can
then give it back to the US government
and the US government has to give you
back the money. So the government is
actually the US government is actually
borrowing money from you in exchange for
a piece of paper.
And there are nations that buy up
tremendous quantities of American uh
bonds, debt bonds, sovereign bonds. So
the Chinese own trillions of dollars of
US debt in this ma in this manner.
Uh and the and so that's that's how the
US has racked up so much debt,
tremendous quantities of debt. If you
look at uh US debt right now, so that's
one way in which the US is has racked up
debt and there are other ways also. Uh
US debt
uh chart do we have chart?
Okay. Do we have something? Let's see.
As you can see how how high it's gone in
the year 2000. It was what was this?
How many million dollars? $5.9
million million.
Now,
so it's this is unsustainable. If the
entire world for example does a bank run
on the US and the whole whole world at
the same time comes and says give us
back our debt, the US will have nothing
to give. So that is the reality of the
US economy. It's a scam. It's an
absolute scam. Who is next after Iran? I
don't know whoever dares to stand up to
the US.
Anand Burukan thank you sir.
Geopolitical dub sir thank you very
much.
Now what is the next question?
Um what is this video says as a
historian if you have been given a good
position in government and government
says do whatever and make India China
allies in the next 5 years I will say
what will be your moves I will tell the
government I don't want your position
because India and China will not be
allies in the next 5 years okay I will
say I cannot take up this position on
that condition the condition is that I
should make India and China allies in
the next 5 years it's not possible
because China sees the world in in a
certain set of ways and you can't change
that that's It's a fundamental
worldview that they have. You cannot
change that. Okay. If if I'm told that
in the next 5 years you need to make
India reach this level in technology or
this level in education or whatever, I
can do that. That's in my control. But
somebody else's attitudes and
perceptions are not something I can
control. Right? You can influence that.
You can try and shape that but there's
no guaranteed outcome. But when it comes
to India itself,
changing the education system, reforming
it or achieving something else in
science or technology, all of that is
entirely in your hands because you
control the resources, you control the
people, you control everything within
the country. That's something you can
definitely
possibly guarantee an outcome of. But
this I don't know.
Okay.
Kumar Kaneska says I sorry but I don't
think we are fully sovereign the way we
paused operation Tindu Russia never
stopped Ukraine operation China if enter
in military operation won't stop okay
sir that's your opinion thank you
warrior says how can bat project its
power globally
India is not in a position to power
project power globally with a $4.3
trillion economy
all right
and of course if you want to genuinely
project power globally. Forget about
globally, first do it locally, right?
First do it locally, how then you have
to ask yourself, okay,
um how does the US project power? So
that's the first thing you have to
learn.
How does the US project power? It
projects power through a multiplicity of
strategies. One strategy is that you
construct military bases extr
territorially. You construct your
military bases on the territories of
other nations
and to do that you have those nations
sign treaties of alliance or whatever
with you which will allow these these
bases to be constructed and operated and
that vitalizes the nation. Then you have
nations form alliances like NATO and the
EU and so on which you can control and
so on. But if you're talking about
projecting military power, you need
military bases that are extr territorial
in nature.
So for that India would need military
bases in the Indian Ocean region. That's
how we do it. And for that you need the
goodwill of the countries. You need the
acquisance of those countries in which
you want to build military bases. And
that happens when you have something to
offer to them. There's always a quid
proquo. There's always a give and take.
Does India have a lot to offer right now
with a $4.3 trillion economy? So my
point is right now let's not talk about
flying before we can learn how to walk
and run and sprint. Yes. And vasilizing
nations. Let's fire in the future.
Um yeah, so that's the deal. Is
vaselizing a necessity for remaining a
sovereign superpower? It it helps a lot.
It helps a lot for sure.
Genie says, "Does our air defense track
the F-35 without Lmberg?" I'm not sure.
I don't know.
Um
no, no, no. says, "Could you please
summarize why and how Israel holds so
much power, especially such stronghold
over the US?" Well, I haven't gone into
the into the details. There is a book by
Professor John Mir Shimemer that that is
about possibly the Israel lobby in the
US or something. I am told that that's
the book to read, but I haven't read it
yet. So, so but it's clear that Israel
has a tremendous amount of hold over the
US and influence over the US. Nobody can
deny that. And I think the details could
be possibly in that book but which I
haven't read yet so I won't be able to
answer the question but u what is said
is that there are lots of influential
and powerful Jewish origin politicians
and business people and so on in the US
uh and they all work together they are
very unified unlike Hindus who are who
are like cats cats can't be herded right
that sort of thing so that's that's how
it happens allegedly
um musk musk musk well thank Thank you
mask maskm sir. Thank you.
Okay. I will not I will only take
geopolitics questions
only. Geopolitics questions.
Um
okay. Sid Barka says, "Can the US kill a
nation's AI ambitions by declining them
access to Nvidia's technology who have a
monopoly for now? Uh can they use Nvidia
Open AI as a weapon? They certainly can
do these things. They are currently
pressurizing Nvidia. The US government
is pressurizing Nvidia to stop sales of
certain chips,
very powerful chips to China and to
nations that could then reroute those
chips to China. So that's already
happening. But when it comes to China,
they are already in the process of
building of of manufacturing their own
highquality chips. So they may be able
to surmount this problem. But when it
comes to other nations where
a proper semiconductor ecosystem doesn't
exist, the US can completely destroy
that nation's EI ambitions by simply
denying access to Nvidia's technology.
Absolutely. So the US can use all of
these uh resources as weapons because
Nvidia is an American company. All of
these companies, all of these platforms
are American platforms which they can
deny the use of to anybody.
Uh Abisheku says my friend says Russia
is responsible for Ukraine China war
Russia Ukraine war as they first invaded
Crimea and now this thought Ukraine is
easy walk but they seem that etc. Well,
everybody has the right to their
opinions and I respect your friend's
right to their to his or her opinion.
Uh Rohan Surja says, "Can Putin be
really really be arrested or is it just
fluff?" When you are on the territory of
another nation,
you are in under the control. So Putin
can't be arrested when he's in Russia,
nobody dares do that. But if Mr. Putin
travels to a different nation or
transits through a nation. For example,
if you're going to nation X, but to go
to nation X, you have to fly over nation
Y and nation Y decides they want to
arrest you. They'll send send fighter
planes to escort to force your plane
down and they arrest you. What can you
do about it? Nothing.
Of course, you can nuke them later, but
that's a different story. So, yeah, it's
possible, right? Why risk it? Why risk
it? Shubankar say Shuhham Kumbharker
says none of our neighbors are aligned
with our interests
mostly. Yeah, that's that's a valid
observation.
Musk Musk Musk. Thank you once again
sir.
Um
is this a geopolitical question? I would
say it is. It's not a dumb question. The
question is why is democracy considered
to be greater than dictatorship? Because
that is the norm that has been created.
It's what everybody has been brainwashed
into into thinking and then they they
give us examples of very bad dictators.
So the Americans installed a whole bunch
of horrible people as dictators in
Africa and then they give those
examples. Look at so and so dictator.
For example, Idiamin. I'm not sure the
Americans installed the Idiamin, but he
when you destroy a continent and and
ruin the place and destroy the culture,
destroy the whole governance system,
then only the worst people will come to
power. So, I am Amin comes to power and
they say, "Look at this guy, such an
evil guy. Look at Saddam Hussein. The
guys were working with Saddam Hussein
for the longest time, but now he's the
he's the example of a evil dictator. Or
look at Muhammad Gaddafi, such an evil
guy, human rights abuser and so and so
on. They install a whole bunch of
dictators all over the place and then
they give those examples. What about Lee
Kuanu?
Well, he was a benevolent dictator,
great man. Great man, right? What about
him and so on? So the thing is it's just
propaganda.
Propaganda. If you have a good system
that throws up the right people, then
even a dictatorship can be super
beneficial.
And what happens in a dictatorship?
Okay, what happens? Assuming it's a good
dictatorship for example, then the
country is run like a corporation
and the dictator is the CEO and the
dictator's minions are the seauite
COO, CFO, CTO, whatever.
And everything is done super fast.
So that really uh speeds up the decision
making and uh the the speed at which
decisions are implemented and executed
and problems are solved and so on. In a
de democracy there's a road for
everything and that's especially a
nation like India. So
right okay
let's take this one. Raji Raj says,
"Russia did not make any technological
progress after the dissolution of the
USSR. So their war tech is of the 80s.
Explains why the Russia Ukraine war is
taking so long. What do I think?" Not
entirely the case. Not all of their
technology is from the 80s. Yes, some of
the strategic aircraft are from the 20th
century. Look at American strategic
aircraft. Many of them are like 70 year
old designs, but they are still
manufactured and they are high quality.
Uh some some designs are timeless. Um,
so not all of Russia's technology is
from the 80s. The tanks are super super
new, super modern. Uh, many of I mean,
what about the Siron missile? What about
the Kinjal missile? Do you think that's
80s technology, sir? Really? You think
so? What about all the drones they're
using? Do you think it's 80s technology?
What about the Sarmat missile? Or what
about the Sukoy 57? Is that 80s
technology? I can give you so many
examples. So, it's not the case. Okay, I
I hope that the examples will convince
you that it's not entirely the case. I'm
sure there will be some technological um
some weaponry that could date back to
the the Cold War. It's possible like
some of the strategic bombers, but they
still work fine. So why why change that?
But those strategic bombers will have
the latest cutting edge frightening
missiles, hypersonic missiles, Mach 9
missiles. So you do what you can with
whatever you have and that doesn't
explain why the Russia Ukraine was
taking so long. That does not it does
it.
Uh
the rational reporter says what type of
what type and quantity of aircraft air
defense and ISR do we need to gain air
dominance over Pakistan like Israel did
over Iran? What budget and time is
required? We already have all the all
everything we need. We already have it,
don't we? In operation synindur, we we
achieved air dominance over Pakistan. We
first knocked down their air defenses.
We knocked down their radars. So, they
were blind. Uh we knocked out their
their Chinese air defense systems. Then
we uh created their their their runways
and we poked holes into their hangars
and stuff and then our aircraft were
flying over Pakistan and there was
nothing the Pakistanis could do. The
runways were created. So we already have
everything we need to gain air dominance
over Pakistan. There's nothing more
extra we need right now.
He's manticor is glad to be a member.
Join after the Chingghistan video. Well,
thank you so much. That's a long time
ago, right? It's like four years ago
now. I I if I'm not mistaken. Thank you
so much. I really appreciate that.
Really I do.
Okay. Now I will once again let me tell
you I will not take non geopolitics
questions in this live stream.
I will not take non- geopolitics
question. I mean I I will simply just
ignore this non- geopolitics questions.
Ah
um Reddi always ready says are we rivals
to China
are
are we a rival to China when were half
their GDP or 2/3 I'm not sure what
you're asking. Are we a rival to China?
We are rival to China. China is our
rival. We are their rival. China is two
and a half times more powerful than us.
But we are still rivals.
That's what I can answer you. I'm not
sure what the I'm I'm not sure if I can
um I can understand everything you're
saying here. R W A. Okay. So yeah,
that's the answer. I think we are out of
super chat. So I'll take some live chat
questions um and then we can
then we can um
later end this. Venita Vijay from uh
Facebook says do you think there will be
a third world war? Well first of all I
let me say that I hope it never happens.
Uh but there are some flash points in
the world that could lead us to a third
world war. flash points like the Ukraine
war in which there is if there is an
escalation
you know for example if the Ukrainians
continue to use long range weapons and
if they end up hitting Moscow or
something then Russia may be tempted may
be required according to the nuclear
doctrine to possibly use nuclear weapons
if they use nuclear weapons then there
could be some response from the west of
similar of a similar kind that could
very quickly lead us up the escalation
ladder and cause a nuclear exchange
which is a third world war So that's one
very dangerous flash point. Ukraine
seems to be going very slowly but it's a
very dangerous flash point for the world
because it can escalate very fast. Then
you have uh the the Middle East region
which which even if the US gets involved
unless the Russians get involved it's
not really a big issue. Obviously it's
bad for the world because it will you
know raise oil prices and all that but
that's not a third world war issue.
China, Taiwan could potentially be a
third world war thing if the US gets
embroiled and if Russia gets pulled in.
India, China is not a third world war
flashoint. It's it's it's a dangerous
flash point for both nations but not a
third world war flashoint. So I think
Ukraine is the most dangerous flash
point right now which could lead us to a
third world war. I hope it doesn't
happen.
Um
okay.
Uh the Mandian says how to protect our
land and marine choke points. Uh how do
you protect choke points? You you
protect them by fortifying the area
militarily. So if you have a choke point
for example, okay, let's let's go to the
map. That's an interesting question. If
we look at the Z map and if you see the
let's take a look at the major choke
points that uh that are relevant to us.
One is the straight of hormones. Now
people will ask why do we care about the
straight of hormones? It's it's so far
away from India. it's between the UAE
and and Persia. But 40 to 50% of our
energy comes from here. So this is
important for us. If so, if this uh this
trade is choked, then we lose access to
about 40 to 50% of the energy we are
importing, right? So that's uh
important. Then we have uh this choke
point Babal Mandib which also you know a
lot of the imports come from there. Then
there is uh Mala which is strategically
important for China not that much for us
but it's something we can control. So
how do we protect these choke points? By
having power projection capabilities
that can uh that can cause us to
dominate these choke points. That's how
we do it. So we need powerful we need a
very powerful navy that can be deployed
on demand to these places. We also need
a very powerful air force that can reach
these regions right and and return. So
that's for that we would perhaps need uh
aircraft carriers or other military
bases in other other parts of the world.
For example, the Anderman islands can
serve as air force bases. Why not? Why
don't we have that? I don't get it. Why
don't we have a naval bases here,
submarine bases here? We should do that.
Uh so that's how we do it. You do it by
fortifying them and by developing the
power projection capabilities that would
lead that would allow you to dominate
these places uh militarily.
All right.
Okay. We uh okay let's take this
question. What if the US interest is to
push back Iran nuclear program but not
regime change? It counterbalances Israel
and ensures weapon sales in Arab
countries. Sir, you are a G. Sir or
ma'am, you're a genius.
Hasn't Isn't that what the US has done?
Isn't that what the US has achieved?
They have pushed back the Iranian
nuclear program by 6 months or so. They
haven't obliterated anything like Mr.
Trump keeps on saying, but they have
pushed back the nuclear program by maybe
6 months. They have made made sure
there's no regime change in in Iran.
They've made sure Israel doesn't get a
big victory.
And now the region is tense, so there'll
be more arms sales in these regions.
Outstanding win-win for the US. So yeah,
there you have it. There you have it.
Good.
Um,
okay. Talik Sue says, "What is India's
economic fallback if the US cuts off um
reliance on India's IT sector or
weaponizes the IT sector? Huge portion
of India's GDP relies on IT exports.
India doesn't seem to have any economic
fallback to that." You see that's a
great question you're you're raising
here and you're highlighting
a very big vulnerability that India has.
So we
like you like you rightly say a
significant portion of our GDP comes
from it it it comes from IT exports
services that we export and and and
software exports and IT exports
essentially.
So that's a the So if this goes away,
it's a big problem for India. Now how
could this go away? One scenario is that
the US decides that it no longer wants
uh India to have access to its IT
market. So it it stops relying on the
Indian IT sector. So India's IT sector
runs out of orders. No, no more clients.
Then what do you do? Who do you sell to?
Right? That's a problem. The other
scenario is going to happen. The other
scenario is even more dangerous is that
AI takes over IT and you don't need IT
contractors anymore.
So right now what what is the Indian IT
sector doing? It is relying on wage
arbitrage.
So in the US a programmer will let's say
hypothetically charge $100 an hour.
Hypothetically $100 an hour. But the
Indian programmer or the Indian company
will have programmers and they will
charge the US clients instead of $100 an
hour, $20 an hour. So it makes sense for
the American companies to to to
outsource the work to Indian companies
that charge just $20 an hour instead of
$100 an hour. That way they can have,
you know, five people do the work that
uh that uh I mean it's five times
cheaper that way. But what if you can
hire AI employees who will do the work
for $2 an hour? It'll be superior to
anything a human being can do. Well,
that is almost upon us now. That time is
almost here.
We already have agentic AI. You already
have these u um what is it called? Clo
code which kind of is kind of going in
the direction of being an u AI employee
of yours. You have tools like cursor
these days which I hear is very good.
You also have other agentic systems. So
we are beginning to go venture into that
territory. Okay. Where AI becomes your
employee and it's superior to humans.
So once give it 6 months, give it one
year and the whole landscape will be
changed. So then if I am an if I have a
US company that needs IT work done and I
am outsourcing it all to India much of
it and now all I will have to do is to
hire AI employees. So I go to I I I
purchase a plan from OpenAI and I get a
100 AI employees and maybe it costs me
$2 an hour per AI employee something and
whatever it is. So it's way cheaper than
India and all I have to do is hire a
couple of managers who will handle the
tasks, allocate the task and ensure that
everything is done properly and do the
QR testing and whatnot. It's super cheap
that way and this will completely
annihilate the Indian IT sector.
So that's that's coming that's coming.
It's going to happen and I don't think
any India India has any answer to this
right now.
Anand Murukhan, thank you very much sir.
Ishan, thank you very much. Where is
Ishan?
Ishan, thank you very much. Um, Haridas
says, "How did 1970s Iraq, once advanced
in science and education, collapse into
instability? Was it due to dictatorship
wars or foreign interference?" So, Iraq
was fairly advanced. It was very
well-governed and organized and
administered. Saddam Hussein was a
dictator, but he did a great job
actually. You know, Iran was a secular
nation. Women were not forced to cover
up or anything. Women worked just like
men. There was complete peace and
harmony. There were no sectarian
troubles, Shia, troubles or any such
thing. Um there was a high quality of
life. There was law and order. No issues
at all in the country and high quality
science, high quality education, all of
that. So what went wrong? First of all,
the Iran Iraq war starts sometime in the
1980s, goes all goes on all the all the
way until 88 or so that devastated both
nations. And this was a proxy war
between the US and Iran.
Okay. So, the US used Saddam Hussein as
a proxy to try and destroy Iran.
And Saddam Hussein, well, he allowed
himself to be used as an as an agent by
the US. So, that was the beginning of
the thing. And then in the early '90s,
the Americans encouraged Saddam Hussein
to invade Kuwait. So he kind of asked
the Americans, would you guys mind if I
invade Kuwait and take over? And they
kind of indicated that they will not
mind too much. The moment he invades
Kuwait, they assemble an invasion force
against Iraq and then they devastate
Iraq. So that's where it all went wrong.
It went on 1980s onwards. It went wrong
1980s onwards gradually.
All right. Um,
ready always ready is now expanding the
question. Will we be a real competitor
to China when we are half their GDP or
twothirds of theirs? I mean a genuine
rival to China also to be a major power
in the world. Look you you are a real
competitor when your system is is is
not just to do what GDP. So even today
we are kind of a rival for China but not
really taken as seriously as China. U
our GDP is 4 point something their GDP
is 18 right trillion.
So they are like 4 and a half times our
about four times our GDP right now. uh
let's say in a few years their GDP is 20
and ours is 10 a hypothetical example
we'll be taken more seriously and China
will take us more seriously and our the
level of competition we will be able to
give them will be more than what we can
give them right now but what if in the
future they are 24
and we are 16 so now we are 2/3 of their
GDP then they'll take us even more
seriously and the competition and
rivalry will intensify so the more the
closer you approach them from a GDP
perspective, the more intense the
rivalry becomes. No question about it.
Especially when you're neighboring
nations. But we will also have to reform
our system to become a real rival to
China. If we continue the system of
mediocrity and corruption allegedly and
so on, then we will never end up being a
real rival to China. So we will need to
uh address all the internal issues that
we have. When you have a 100 million
plus illegal immigrants living squatting
on your territory, you're not going to
be a real rival to China. You have all
these problems that need to be solved.
So it's not about just about GDP, it's
about so many other things. But yeah, if
we get all these things right, we will
be real rivals to China.
Uh
Ram Raman Raman says, "What's your
opinion on RAC? Is it positive?" RA is a
symbolic forum and it can be a great
forum, but it won't be because China
exists in the forum and China is the
spoiler. China is the spoiler in RIC and
China is also the major spoiler in
bricks. It is not India that is creating
problems in bricks or RA. It is China
that is the spoiler. China is hostile to
Russia. It is hostile to India. It
pretends to be everybody's friend. It
lectures the world about nice things but
its actions are those of a bully. So ra
is just a symbolic forum. It will never
amount to anything significant
geopolitically.
Um,
Adita Jooshi says, "What's your what
about recent developments in relations
between India and North Korea? Opening
of an Indian embassy in North Korea. Do
you foresee any future tactical strong
relations with North Korea?" Um, it's
it's good that we have now we're now
going to have an ambassador in North
Korea and uh that's that's good. It's a
it's a positive move by India. Do I
foresee uh future tactical strong
relations with North Korea? I don't
foresee that. The reason is that North
Korea is a Chinese vasal. Okay. And uh
they are very strongly uh influenced by
China. They are strongly dependent on
China and Russia for a lot of things
mainly China. And because of that it's
not possible for us to have strong
tactical or strategic relations with
North Korea. I think the appointment of
an ambassador to North Korea is kind of
a signal to the US.
It's actually it's it's actually a
message that we are sending to the US
that you guys are you know you're
playing with Pakistan and you're
vasalizing Bangladesh and supporting
Pakistan investing in Pakistan hurting
our interests we can also do these
things that's the kind of message we are
sending diplomatically beyond that I
don't see too much more to this
what's the story behind China's economic
miracle that it poses a threat to the US
and the world today are there any books
or sources focusing on that I'm sure
there are lots But I can't remember any
of them. China's econom economic
miracle. What's the story? The story in
long and short, I mean in short is that
China was very very inspired by Lee
Kuwanu and what Lee Kwanu achieved in
Singapore in just a generation, in just
20 years. And the Chinese sent
bureaucrats and government officials to
Singapore to study how Lee Kwanu
achieved what he achieved. And then they
sought to implement that in China which
was easier said than done because
Singapore is a a city and China is this
gigantic nation. Uh but they slowly
steadily opened up their economy and
used it very very very smartly to become
a manufacturing power. That's the main
economic miracle and then they reformed
the education system and they poured in
the money into other sectors and so on
and they became that's that's how it
happened. So they were aided and abetted
by the US. The US imagined that if China
becomes economic economically
prosperous, they'll become a democracy.
Well, that's not quite happened. So
that's kind of the story in brief of
China's economic miracle.
Okay, let me take one or two questions
more and then it will be the end of this
live stream. This was a pretty good live
stream actually. I enjoyed it mostly um
because I did not take non- geopolitics
questions as I had said. Um
now look this is the kind of mindset
lots of Indians have
sir this is a channel where we do
positivity
I we are aware of all the problems in
India lots of problems exists but if you
say stop dreaming then I'm going to have
to ban you from this channel because I
don't I don't need such negativity here
why should you stop dreaming then this
nation has more potential than anybody
else on the planet. It's just that we
have our self-imposed limitations
which need to be
dealt with. Last question for today.
Does India have any of its own vasals?
We don't. Officially, we don't. Okay,
that's the answer. All right, everybody.
Thank you so much for the questions. I'm
going to end this live stream right
here. 2 hours plus as always. Uh so, it
was fun. I enjoyed doing this and uh
thank you so much for all your
questions. Keep learning, keep asking
questions, keep keep please keep raising
your standards. One thing that
frustrates me often and I'm sorry if my
frustration is sometimes visible, but
after all these years of answering your
questions, I'm hoping for better
questions. I'm hoping for
some some some
raising of standards. Maybe I'll teach
you step by step how to raise standards,
but that's something we can do in the
future. So anyway, thank you so much. I
really appreciate your viewership. Uh,
and I look forward to seeing you next
week. I'll put out the put put out the
schedule for next week, probably
tomorrow. And I look forward to seeing
you next week. Thank you so much for
everything. Take care. I'll see you
soon. Bye-bye.